Beth El Temple Collection 0010.002.002
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Beth El Temple
1953-2012
0010.002.002
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
1.5 Cubic feet 10 boxes, 2 boxes of photographs and several scrapbooks
Beth El Temple was founded in West Hartford in 1954 by a group of seven couples from The Emanuel Synagogue in Hartford. The temple's first Rabbi, Stanley Kessler, was appointed in September of that year. Kessler would be noted for his involvement in the civil rights movement and other causes. Rabbi Kessler served as religious leader of the Temple until his retirement in 1992. At that time, Rabbi James Rosen was appointed and Rabbi Kessler became Rabbi Emeritus.
Beth El was founded on democratic principles. All members paid the same membership fee and had an equal vote. Almost from the beginning, women as well as men were entitled to vote on behalf of their families.
Before moving into its own building, the congregation held services at the Friends's Meeting House on South Quaker Lane. The congregation began construction on its own building starting with the Education Wing in 1954. The Temple Sanctuary was completed in 1963. Since that time, chapel and sculpture gardens have been added.
Emanuel and Beth El maintained a joint religious school from 1953 until 1955. The joint school met first at Emanuel and then at the Robinson School. When the Beth El Education Wing was completed, Beth El established its own school.
By 1980, the congregation numbered almost 700 families. Today, with a membership of over 1,000 households, Beth El is one of the largest Conservative congregations in New England.
Feldman, Abraham J., Rabbi, b.1893, Ukraine, Russia; Fox, Jacob, Retailer, Vice-president, G. Fox & Co., 03/26/1856 - 02/23/1936, Ellsworth, ME; Kessler, Stanley, Rabbi; Wise, Isidore, Executive Merchant, 11/19/1866 - 01/25/1956, Hartford, CT; Conservative Judaism; Synagogues
- Series I: A
  - Anniversary/Congregation/10th, 1963, 1963-1963
  - Anniversary/Congregation/13th, 1967, 1967-1967
  - Anniversary/Congregation/18th, 1971, 1971-1971
  - Anniversary/Congregation/20th, 1973-1974
  - Anniversary/Congregation/25th, 1978-1979
  - Anniversary/Congregation/30th, 1983-1984
  - Anniversary/Congregation/35th, 1988-1989
  - Anniversary/Congregation/40th, 1992-1994
  - Anniversary/Congregation/50th, 2001-2004
  - Anniversary/Congregation/50th/Archive Notes 2001-2004
  - Awards, undated
  - Awards/Elie Wiesel, Kessler Award, 2006, includes autographed program and two photographs, 2006-2006
    Wiesel, Elie, Author, Doctor
- Series II: B-D
  - Board of Directors/Annual Meeting, undated
  - Board of Directors/Members, undated
  - Board of Directors/Meetings/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Board of Directors/Officers, undated
  - Board of directors/Presidents/Bernstein, Stuart, undated
  - Board of directors/Presidents/Feinstein, Arthur W., undated
  - Board of directors/Presidents/Rachlin, Joseph, undated
  - Board of directors/Presidents/Ludgin. Louis, undated
  - Board of directors/Presidents/Weiner, undated
  - Board of directors/Presidents/Weinstein, Arthur, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Chapel, 1989, 1989-1989
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Dedication, June 1955, 1955-1955
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Education Wing/First Construction, 1955, 1955-1955
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Education Wing/Cornerstone, 1955, 1955-1955
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Renovation, 2002-2003
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Sanctuary, 1963, 1963-1963
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Sculpture Garden, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave./Renovation, 2002-2003
  - Calendars of Events and Programs, undated
  - Cemetery, undated
  - Chai Society, undated
  - Charitable Activities/Social Action, undated
  - Constitution and by-laws, undated
  - Constitution and by-laws/Women's vote, 1955, 1955-1955
  - Contributions to charities, undated
- Series III: D-G
  - Education/Adult Education, undated
  - Education/Adult Education/Morning Book Review Group, 1965, 1965-1965
  - Education/Adult Education/Scholar in Residence, undated
  - Education/School/Activities, undated
  - Education/School/Activities/Israel, undated
  - Education/School/Activities\Yearbook, 1951, 1951-1951
  - Education/School/Activities/Graduation and Confirmation, undated
  - Education/School/Planning, undated
  - Education/School/Programs and Curriculum, undated
  - Financial, undated
  - Financial, 1950s, 1950-1959
  - Fundraising/Capital Campaign, 2001, 2001-2001
  - Fundraising/Endowment, undated
  - Fundraising/Miscellaneous, undated
- Series IV: He -Historical Highlights
  - Health and Safety, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Cemetery, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Financial, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Groundbreaking, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Meetings, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Members, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Miscellaneous/Primary Material, c. 1954, 1954-1954
  - Historical Highlights/Miscellaneous/Secondary Material, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Newspaper clippings, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Officers and Trustees, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Picnic, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Real Estate, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Robinson School, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Newsletter/Temple Topics, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Services, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Special Bulletins, undated
  - Historical Highlights/Zoning, undated
- Series V: Ho-M
  - Holidays/Chanukah, undated
  - Holidays/High Holidays, undated
  - Holidays/New Year, undated
  - Holidays/Passover, undated
  - Holidays/Purim, undated
  - Holidays/Simchas Torah, undated
  - Holidays/Tisha B'Av, undated
  - Holidays/Yom Ha Atzmaut, undated
  - Holocaust, undated
  - Interfaith Activities, undated
  - Interfaith Activities/Notes, 1962, 1962-1962
  - Interfaith Activities/Union Thanksgiving Services, 1950s-1960s, 1950-1959
  - Judaica Art Collection, undated
  - Members and Membership, undated
  - Members/Individuals, undated
  - Members/Gift book listing names of members who contributed to various funds., undated
  - Men's Club, undated
  - Mitzvah Day, 2000-, undated
  - Music/Cantors, undated
  - Music/Concerts, undated
  - Music/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Music/Organ, undated
  - Music and Arts Committee/Art Exhibition, 1995, 1955-1955
- Series VI: Newsletters, 1950s-1990
  - Newsletter, 1950s, 1950-1959
  - Newsletter, 1960s, 1960-1969
  - Newsletter, 1971-1972
  - Newsletter, 1973-1974
  - Newsletter, 1975-1976
  - Newsletter, 1980, 1980-1989
  - Newsletter, 1984-1986
  - Newsletter, 1987-1988
  - Newsletter, 1989-1990
- Series VII: Newsletters, 1991-2000s: Newspaper clippings/miscelleaneous
  - Newsletter, 1991-1992
  - Newsletter, 1993-1994
  - Newsletter, 1995-1997
  - Newsletter, 1998, 1998-1998
  - Newsletter, 1999, 1999-1999
  - Newsletter, 2000, 2000-2000
  - Newsletter, 2001, 2001-2001
  - Newsletter, 2002, 2002-2002
  - Newsletter, 2003, 2003-2003
  - Newsletter, 2004, 2004-2004
  - Newsletter, 2005, 2005-2005
  - Newsletter/College-Age Youth, 1980s-1990s, 1980-1999
- Series VIII: O-R
  - Public Relations, undated
  - Rabbis/, undated
  - Rabbis/Garber, Ilana, undated
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley, undated
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/appointment, 1954, 1954-1954
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Awards, undated
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Newspaper Clippings, 1950s, 1950-1959
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Newspaper Clippings, 1960s, 1960-1969
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Newspaper Clippings, 1970s, 1970-1979
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Newspaper Clippings, 1980s, 1980-1989
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Newspaper Clippings, 1990s, 1990-1999
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Newspaper Clippings, 2000s, 2000-2009
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/ Oral history interview notes, undated
  - Rabbis/Rosen, James, undated
  - Rabbis/Rosen, James/Newspaper Clippings, undated
  - Ritual Matters/Bar and Bat Mitzvah, undated
  - Ritual Matters/Bar and Bat Mitzvah/Sondick Barbara\Beth El's first Bat Mitzvah, 1954, 1954-1954
  - Ritual Matters/Bar and Bat Mitzvah/Special Needs/See also Rabbis/ Rosen, James, undated
  - Ritual Matters/Bar and Bat Mitzvah/Tutoring, 1961, 1961-1961
  - Ritual Matters/Healing Services, undated
  - Ritual Matters/Torah restoration, undated
  - Ritual Matters/Yizkor Books "Books of Remembrance", undated
- Series IX: - Sisterhood/E
  - Sephardic programs, undated
  - Shabbat/Innovative Programs, 2000s, undated
  - Shabbat/Shabbat Events/Special programs, undated
  - Shabbat/Shabbat Handouts, undated
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, n.d. probably 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, n.d. probably 1970s, undated
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1960
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1963
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1964
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1965
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1966
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1967
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1968
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1969
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1970
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1971
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1972
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1973
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1974
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1975
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1976
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1977
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1979
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1980
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1981
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1982
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1983
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1984
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1985
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1986
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1987
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1988
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1989
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1990
  - Sisterhood, Art Exhibition, 1992
  - Sisterhood/Awards, undated
  - Sisterhood/Board of Directors/Annual Meetings/reports, 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Board of Directors/Minutes, 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Board of Directors/Members, undated
  - Sisterhood/By-Laws, undated
  - Sisterhood/Children's Programs, undated
  - Sisterhood/conferences, undated
  - Sisterhood/Contributions to Charities, undated
  - Sisterhood/Correspondence, undated
- Series X: Sisterhood/F-Z
  - Sisterhood/Financial, 1950s-1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Fundraising/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Sisterhood/Historical Highlights, undated
  - Sisterhood/Installation, 1950s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Installation, 1960s-1980s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Installation, 1990s-2000s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Installation/Luncheon, 1964, undated
  - Sisterhood/Judaism in the Home Tour/Brochures, 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Judaism in the Home Tour/Newspaper clippings, 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Judaism in the Home Tour/Miscellaneous, 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Meetings, undated
  - Sisterhood/Men's Club, joint programs/Art Exhibitions, undated
  - Sisterhood/Men's Club, joint programs/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Sisterhood/New Year Cards, undated
  - Sisterhood/Newsletter/Sisterhood News, undated
  - Sisterhood/Notes, undated
  - Sisterhood/Officers and Members, undated
  - Sisterhood/Oneg Shabbat Notebook, 1967-1978
  - Sisterhood/Programs, undated
  - Sisterhood/Sermonettes, 1960s, undated
  - Sisterhood/Stationary, undated
  - Social Events/, undated
  - Social Events/Plays, undated
  - Social Events/Tribute to Founding Members, May 1999
  - Soviet Jewry, undated
  - Staff Members, undated
  - Strategic Planning, 1999, undated
  - Youth Groups/, undated
  - Youth Groups/, undated
  - Youth Groups/Kadima, undated
  - Youth Groups/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Youth Groups/United Synagogue Youth (USY), undated
  - Women/Rosh Hadesh Group, undated
- Series XI: Photographs A-R
  - Anniversaries/Congregation's/30th, 1983-1984
  - Anniversaries/Congregation's/40th, 1993-1994
  - Beth El at Camp Ramah, undated
  - Board of Directors, undated
  - Board of Directors/Presidents, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Architect, Kane, Joe, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/chapel/construction, 1986-1987
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/chapel/dedication, 1986-1987
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/East Wing/dedication, 2002
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Education Wing/Dedication, 1955
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Education Wing/Dedication, 1961
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Menorah/dedication, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Sanctuary/construction, 1961
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Sanctuary/oversize in Hebrew Home oversize box, undated
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/Sculpture, 1965
  - Buildings/2626 Albany Ave. West Hartford/vestry/ground-breaking, 1954
  - Cantors, undated
  - Cemetery, undated
  - Chai Society/programs, undated
  - Conventions, undated
  - Early History, undated
  - Early History/See also OVERSIZE photos – contains several enlargements, undated
  - Education/School/Activities, undated
  - Groups/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Weddings, undated
  - Members, undated
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley, undated
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/Rabbi and Mrs. Kessler, 50th wedding anniversary, 1997
  - Rabbis/Kessler, Stanley/retirement, undated
  - Rabbis/Rosen, James/Installation, 1992
  - Ritual Matters/Bar and Bat Mitzvah/Special Needs/, undated
  - Sisterhood/Art Exhibitions, undated
- Series XII: Photographs S-Z
  - Sisterhood/Book club, undated
  - Sisterhood/Conventions and Meetings, undated
  - Sisterhood/Early History, undated
  - Sisterhood/Social Activities/Fashion show, 1997
  - Sisterhood/Social Activities/Judaism in the home, 1991
  - Sisterhood/Visit to Jewish Theological Seminary, 1960
  - Social Action activities, undated
  - Social Activities/Cantor's concert, undated
  - Social Activities/Picnic, 1954
  - Social Activities/Plays, undated
  - Social Activities/Talent Show, 1990s, undated
  - Social Activities/USS Beth El, 1980s, undated
  - Trips/Israel, undated
  - Trips/New York Jewish Museum, undated
  - Visit to Jewish Theological Seminary, 1953